A few words on pronunciation. I'd like to introduce you to the pronunciation guide
outlines in the following chart. There aren't too many characters that are
different from the standard alphabet, but just so you'll be familiar with them, look
at the chart. It shows eight tense vowels and six lax vowels and semi-vowels. Tense
vowels, lax vowels. In some books, tense vowels are called long and lax vowels are
called short. Since you'll be learning how to lengthen vowels when they come before a
voiced consonant, it would be confusing to say that hen has a long, short vowel. It's
more descriptive to say that it has a lax vowel that is doubled or lengthened. Here
are the tense vowels. A, take. E, eat. I, ice. O, hope. O, smooth. ah, caught, ah,
cat, ow, down, here are the lax vowels, eh, get, ih, it, uh, took, uh, some, and
the semi-vowels, ur, hur, ul, dull. Now, although this may look like a lot of
characters to learn, there are really only four new ones, ah, ah, uh, and uh. Under
tense vowels, you'll notice that the vowels that say their own names simply
have a line over them, a-e-i-o-u. There are three other tense vowels. First, ah is
pronounced like the sound you make when the doctor wants to see your throat, or
when you loosen a tight belt and sit down in a soft chair. Ah. Next you'll find ah,
a combination of the tense vowel ah and the lax vowel eh. It is similar to the
noise that a goat or a lamb makes, half, last, chance. The last one is ow, a
combination of ah and oh. This is a very common sound, usually written as O-W or O
-U in words like down or round. A tense vowel requires you to use a lot of facial
muscles to produce it. If you say E, you must stretch your lips back. For OO, you
must round your lips forward. For AH, you drop your jaw down. For AH, you'll drop
your jaw far down and back. For A, bring your lips back and drop your jaw a bit.
For I, drop your jaw for the ah part of the sound and pull it back up for the e
part. And for O, round the lips, drop the jaw, and pull back up into ooh. An
American O is really oh-ooh. Now you try it. Repeat after me. E, ooh, ay, ah, ah,
I, oh. A lax vowel, on the other hand, is very reduced. In fact, you don't need to
move your face at all. You only need to move the back of your tongue and your
throat. These sounds are very different from most other languages. Under lax
vowels, there are four reduced vowel sounds starting with the Greek letter
epsilon, pronounced e, the letter i, pronounced i, and the u with two dots,
pronounced u, which is a combination of i and u, and the schwa, pronounced u. Most
reduced, most relaxed sound that we can produce. It is also the most common sound
in English. The semi-vowels are the American R, pronounced er, which is the
schwa plus R, and the American L, which is the schwa plus L. Voice consonants?
Unvoiced consonants? A consonant is a sound that causes two points of your mouth
to come into contact in three locations. The lips, the tip of the tongue, and the
throat. A consonant can either be unvoiced, whispered, or voiced, spoken,
and it can appear at the beginning, middle, or end of a word. You'll notice
that for some categories, a particular sound doesn't exist in English. parry,
berry, apple, able, mop, mob, ferry, very, afraid, avoid, off, of, stew, zoo, racist,
raises face phase sheet pressure pleasure crush garage to do pedal pedal not nod
choke joke gaucho gouger rich ridge think that ether either tooth Smooth, come, gum,
bicker, bigger, pick, pig, accent, exit, tax, tags, yes, player, day, wool, shower,
now, his, ahead, late, collect, towel, rate, correct, tower, me, swimmer, Same.
Next. Connect. Man. Finger. Ring. Pronunciation points. In many
dictionaries, you may find a character that looks like an upside-down V and
another character that's an upside-down E, the schwa. There's a linguistic
distinction between the two, but they're pronounced exactly the same. Since you
can't hear the difference between these two sounds, we'll just be using the
indicate the schwa sound. It's pronounced uh. The second point is that we don't
differentiate between ah and aw. The a with two dots is pronounced ah. The
backward c is more or less pronounced aw. This aw sound has a back e sound to it,
and as it's not common to the entire United States, it won't be included here.
R can be considered a semivowel. One characteristic of a vowel is that nothing
in the mouth touches anything else. R definitely falls into that category. So in
the exercises throughout the book, it'll be treated not so much as a consonant, but
as a vowel. The OU sound is usually indicated by A with two dots U, which
would be OU. This may have been accurate at some point in some locations, now
generally, ow. Town is town, how is how, loud is loud, and so on. Besides voiced
and unvoiced, there are two words that come up in pronunciation. These are
sibilant and plosive. When you say the S sound, you can feel the air sliding out
over the tip of your tongue. This is a sibilant. When you say the P sound, you
can feel the air popping out from between your lips. This is a plosive. Be aware
that there are two sounds that are sometimes mistakenly taught as sibilants
but are actually plosives, TH and V. However, instead of words like plosive and
sibilant, we'll be using commonly used words like hissed, buzzed, and popped to
refer to consonants. For particular points of pronunciation that pertain to your own
language, refer to the Nationality Guides. Vowel chart, ee-beat, ae-bait, ii-bit, ee
-bet, ow-about, ae-bat.